{
  "reference_number": "11962",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Climate change is a con but we do need targets on specific polluters. The process should be in consultation with the public and\n\n must require a 75% majority in the House so that it cannot be repealed, unless by a similar majority."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Too early to set a target now."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Given our isolation and small contribution to the global problem of pollution, we should only implement and act upon targets if other\n\n larger countries do the same."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Absolutely."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "There is a disconnect between a supposed 2050 target which is 32 years away, and having a 15 year budget. If the Government was\n serious about this it would align the 2. Too early for a budget."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Poor choices. Why only the last budget? See comments above regarding the 32 year [project with 15 years of budgets which is\n nonsense. Any Government should be able to change any and all budgets with the same majority (i.e. 50%+ or 75%+) given this is a\n long term project and circumstances change."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Any Government should be able to change any and all budgets. See above."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Why focus on just carbon? There are plenty of other noxious pollutants we need to deal with. Definitely a plan is needed to achieve\n\ntargets but again the choices are poor and the Government should look at all pollutants."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "That citizen taxpayer isn't footing the bill for whack job ideas that the rest of the World does not also commit to. Start by ensuring that\nInternational businesses operating in NZ pay their fair share of tax which can then be used for whatever the Government wants,\n\nincluding reducing pollution if that is the best way to spend money (this is assuming other more important issues have been solved\nsuch as child poverty and homelessness)."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Another trough from which troughers can feast until 2050? A global problem needs local solutions - push this onto the Councils with\n\nadditional funding from Central Government."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Poor choices. We don;t need a Climate Change Commission. See comment above about local councils."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "No comment."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "No no no no no. The climate has been changing for 4 billion years. Deal with the real issue which is pollution, provided other larger\n\ncountries also do their part."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "No no no no no. The climate has been changing for 4 billion years. Deal with the real issue which is pollution, provided other larger\ncountries also do their part."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "No no no no no. The climate has been changing for 4 billion years. Deal with the real issue which is pollution, provided other larger\ncountries also do their part."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "We don't need another trough.\nYou have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
